CH: To what extent is what happened, though, in part, just an unintended consequence, that the traditional media that you worked in had this curation-mediation role, where certain norms were observed, certain stories would be rejected because they weren't credible, but now that the standard for publication and for amplification is just interest, attention, excitement, click, "Did it get clicked on?" "Send it out there!" and that's what's -- is that part of what's caused the problem? CA: I think it's a big problem, and we saw this in the election of 2016, where the idea of "clickbait" was very sexy and very attractive, and so all these fake news sites and fake news items were not just haphazardly and by happenstance being put out there, there's been a whole industry in the creation of fake news in parts of Eastern Europe, wherever, and you know, it's planted in real space and in cyberspace. So I think that, also, the ability of our technology to proliferate this stuff at the speed of sound or light, just about -- we've never faced that before. And we've never faced such a massive amount of information which is not curated by those whose profession leads them to abide by the truth, to fact-check and to maintain a code of conduct and a code of professional ethics. CH: Many people here may know people who work at Facebook or Twitter and Google and so on. They all seem like great people with good intention -- let's assume that. If you could speak with the leaders of those companies, what would you say to them? CA: Well, you know what -- I'm sure they are incredibly well-intentioned, and they certainly developed an unbelievable, game-changing system, where everybody's connected on this thing called Facebook. And they've created a massive economy for themselves and an amazing amount of income. I would just say, "Guys, you know, it's time to wake up and smell the coffee and look at what's happening to us right now." Mark Zuckerberg wants to create a global community. I want to know: What is that global community going to look like? I want to know where the codes of conduct actually are. Mark Zuckerberg said -- and I don't blame him, he probably believed this -- that it was crazy to think that the Russians or anybody else could be tinkering and messing around with this avenue. And what have we just learned in the last few weeks? That, actually, there has been a major problem in that regard, and now they're having to investigate it and figure it out. Yes, they're trying to do what they can now to prevent the rise of fake news, but, you know, it went pretty unrestricted for a long, long time. So I guess I would say, you know, you guys are brilliant at technology; let's figure out another algorithm. Can we not? CH: An algorithm that includes journalistic investigation -- CA: I don't really know how they do it, but somehow, you know -- filter out the crap! (Laughter) And not just the unintentional -- (Applause) but the deliberate lies that are planted by people who've been doing this as a matter of warfare for decades. The Soviets, the Russians -- they are the masters of war by other means, of hybrid warfare. And this is a -- this is what they've decided to do. It worked in the United States, it didn't work in France, it hasn't worked in Germany. During the elections there, where they've tried to interfere, the president of France right now, Emmanuel Macron, took a very tough stand and confronted it head on, as did Angela Merkel. CH: There's some hope to be had from some of this, isn't there? That the world learns. We get fooled once, maybe we get fooled again, but maybe not the third time. Is that true? CA: I mean, let's hope. But I think in this regard that so much of it is also about technology, that the technology has to also be given some kind of moral compass. I know I'm talking nonsense, but you know what I mean. CH: We need a filter-the-crap algorithm with a moral compass -- CA: There you go. CH: I think that's good. CA: No -- "moral technology." We all have moral compasses -- moral technology. CH: I think that's a great challenge. CA: You know what I mean. CH: Talk just a minute about leadership. You've had a chance to speak with so many people across the world. I think for some of us -- I speak for myself, I don't know if others feel this -- there's kind of been a disappointment of: Where are the leaders? So many of us have been disappointed -- Aung San Suu Kyi, what's happened recently, it's like, "No! Another one bites the dust." You know, it's heartbreaking. (Laughter) Who have you met who you have been impressed by, inspired by? CA: Well, you talk about the world in crisis, which is absolutely true, and those of us who spend our whole lives immersed in this crisis -- I mean, we're all on the verge of a nervous breakdown. So it's pretty stressful right now. And you're right -- there is this perceived and actual vacuum of leadership, and it's not me saying it, I ask all these -- whoever I'm talking to, I ask about leadership. I was speaking to the outgoing president of Liberia today, [Ellen Johnson Sirleaf,] who -- (Applause) in three weeks' time, will be one of the very rare heads of an African country who actually abides by the constitution and gives up power after her prescribed term. She has said she wants to do that as a lesson. But when I asked her about leadership, and I gave a quick-fire round of certain names, I presented her with the name of the new French president, Emmanuel Macron. And she said -- I said, "So what do you think when I say his name?" And she said, "Shaping up potentially to be a leader to fill our current leadership vacuum." I thought that was really interesting. Yesterday, I happened to have an interview with him. I'm very proud to say, I got his first international interview. It was great. It was yesterday. And I was really impressed. I don't know whether I should be saying that in an open forum, but I was really impressed. (Laughter) And it could be just because it was his first interview, but -- I asked questions, and you know what? He answered them! (Laughter) (Applause) There was no spin, there was no wiggle and waggle, there was no spend-five-minutes- to-come-back-to-the-point. I didn't have to keep interrupting, which I've become rather renowned for doing, because I want people to answer the question. And he answered me, and it was pretty interesting. And he said -- CH: Tell me what he said. CA: No, no, you go ahead. CH: You're the interrupter, I'm the listener. CA: No, no, go ahead. CH: What'd he say? CA: OK. You've talked about nationalism and tribalism here today. I asked him, "How did you have the guts to confront the prevailing winds of anti-globalization, nationalism, populism when you can see what happened in Brexit, when you could see what happened in the United States and what might have happened in many European elections at the beginning of 2017?" And he said, "For me, nationalism means war. We have seen it before, we have lived through it before on my continent, and I am very clear about that." So he was not going to, just for political expediency, embrace the, kind of, lowest common denominator that had been embraced in other political elections. And he stood against Marine Le Pen, who is a very dangerous woman. CH: Last question for you, Christiane. TED is about ideas worth spreading. If you could plant one idea into the minds of everyone here, what would that be? CA: I would say really be careful where you get your information from; really take responsibility for what you read, listen to and watch; make sure that you go to the trusted brands to get your main information, no matter whether you have a wide, eclectic intake, really stick with the brand names that you know, because in this world right now, at this moment right now, our crises, our challenges, our problems are so severe, that unless we are all engaged as global citizens who appreciate the truth, who understand science, empirical evidence and facts, then we are just simply going to be wandering along to a potential catastrophe. So I would say, the truth, and then I would come back to Emmanuel Macron and talk about love. I would say that there's not enough love going around. And I asked him to tell me about love. I said, "You know, your marriage is the subject of global obsession." (Laughter) "Can you tell me about love? What does it mean to you?" I've never asked a president or an elected leader about love. I thought I'd try it. And he said -- you know, he actually answered it. And he said, "I love my wife, she is part of me, we've been together for decades." But here's where it really counted, what really stuck with me. He said, "It is so important for me to have somebody at home who tells me the truth." So you see, I brought it home. It's all about the truth. (Laughter) CH: So there you go. Truth and love. Ideas worth spreading. Christiane Amanpour, thank you so much. That was great. (Applause) CA: Thank you. CH: That was really lovely. CA: Thank you.
CH: Hasta que punto es lo que pasó, en parte, solo una consecuencia no deseada, que el medio tradicional en el que trabajaste tenía un rol curativo-mediador, donde ciertas normas fueron observadas, ciertas historias serían rechazadas porque no eran creíbles, pero ahora que el estándar para la publicación y la amplificación es solo interés, atención. emoción, hacer clic. "¿Le hicieron clic?" "Envíenlo" y eso eso pasó. ¿Es parte de lo que causó el problema? CA: Creo que hay un gran problema y lo vimos en la elección de 2016, donde la idea de"clickbait" era muy sexy y atractiva y así todos esos sitios de noticias falsas y artículos de noticias falsas no eran publicados al azar y por coincidencia. Existe toda una industria en la creación de noticias falsas en partes de Europa del Este, donde sea, y esté plantada en el espacio real y en el ciberespacio. Y creo también que la habilidad de nuestra tecnología para hacer proliferar estas cosas a la velocidad del sonido o de la luz a tal punto nunca la habíamos enfrentado jamás. Y no habíamos enfrentado una cantidad enorme de información que no estuviera revisada por aquellos cuyas profesión los lleva a aceptar la verdad a chequear hechos y a mantener un código de conducta y un código de ética profesional. CH: Muchas personas aquí deben conocer gente que trabaja en Facebook, Twitter, Google y demás. Todos parecen personas geniales con buenas intenciones. Vamos a asumir eso. Si pudieses hablar con los lideres de esas compañías, ¿qué les dirías? CA: Bueno, estoy segura de que tienen muy buenas intenciones y que ciertamente desarrollaron un sistema innovador increíble, donde todos están conectados en esta cosa llamada Facebook. Y han creado una economía masiva para ellos y tienen unas ganancias increíbles. Yo diría, "Chicos, saben, es tiempo de despertar y oler el café y mirar que es lo que está pasándonos ahora. Mark Zuckerberg quiere crear una comunidad global. Yo quiero saber: ¿Cómo será la comunidad global? Quiero saber donde están los códigos de conducta. Mark Zuckerberg dijo, y no lo culpo, probablemente lo creía que es un locura pensar que los rusos o quien sea estuvieran manipulando por esta vía. ¿Y que aprendimos en las últimas semanas? Esto, en realidad, ha sido un problema grave en ese aspecto y ahora tenemos que investigarlo y descubrirlo. Sí, están intentando hacer lo que pueden ahora para prevenir el aumento de las noticias falsas pero, ya sabes, fue bastante ilimitada por un largo periodo de tiempo. Entonces supongo que les diría Uds. son brillantes en tecnología; descifremos otro algoritmo. ¿Se puede? CH: Un algoritmo que incluya una investigación periodística CA: No sé cómo se debe hacer, pero de alguna forma ¡filtren la mierda! (Risas) Y no solo lo involuntario, (Aplausos) sino también las mentiras deliberadas plantadas por personas que lo hacen desde hace décadas. Los soviéticos, los rusos son los amos de la guerra con otras tácticas de conflicto híbrido. Y esto es lo que decidieron hacer. Funcionó en EE. UU. no funcionó en Francia, no ha funcionado en Alemania. Durante las elecciones allá donde intentaron interferir, el presidente de Francia ahora Emmanuel Macron, tomo una posición muy fuerte y lo confrontó igual que Angela Merkel. CH: ¿Hay algo de esperanza de tener algo así? Que el mundo aprenda. No engañaron una vez, tal vez nos engañaron de nuevo, pero tal vez no la tercera. ¿Es la verdad? CA: Supongo, esperemos. Pero creo esto también es sobre la tecnología, que la tecnología se le tiene que otorgar una especie de brújula moral. Sé que estoy diciendo tonterías, pero ya sabes a lo que me refiero CH :Necesitamos un algoritmo filtra-mierda con una brújula moral. CA: Así es, eso es. CH: Pienso que es bueno. CA: No. "Tecnología moral". Todos tenemos brújulas morales, tecnología moral. CH: Creo que es un gran desafío. CA: Sabes a lo que me refiero. CH: Hablemos ahora sobre liderazgo. Tuviste la oportunidad de hablar con muchas personas de todo el mundo. Creo para algunos de nosotros, hablo por mí, pues no sé, si todos se sienten así, hay una especie de decepción: ¿Dónde están los líderes? Muchos de Uds. están decepcionados. Aung San Suu Kyi, lo que pasó recientemente, es "¡No! Otro que muerde el polvo" Te rompe el corazón. (Risas) ¿A quién has conocido que te ha impresionado, que te ha inspirado? CA: Hablas del mundo en crisis, lo que es absolutamente verdad, y aquellos de nosotros que hemos pasado nuestras vidas inmersas en esta crisis, quiero decir, que estamos todos al borde de un ataque nervioso. Ahora mismo es muy estresante. Y tienes razón, hay un vacío perceptible actual en el liderazgo. Y no es que yo lo diga, lo pregunto siempre, a todos los que les hablo, les pregunto sobre liderazgo. Hablaba con la extrovertida presidente de Liberia hoy, Ellen Johnson Sirleaf, quien (Aplausos) en un periodo de tres semanas, será una de las escasas líderes de un país africano que acata la Constitución y entrega el mandato una vez cumplido su periodo. Ella ha dicho que lo que quiere hacer es dar una lección. Pero cuando le pregunté sobre el liderazgo, y mencioné fugazmente un grupo de ciertos nombres, le mencioné el nombre del nuevo presidente francés, Emmanuel Macron. Y ella... Yo pregunté, "¿Qué piensas cuando digo ese nombre?" Y ella dijo, "Está formándose potencialmente para ser un líder que llene el actual vacío de liderazgo." Pensé que era muy interesante. Ayer tuve una entrevista con él. Estoy orgullosa de decir, que obtuve su primera entrevista internacional. Fue genial, fue ayer. Y estaba muy impresionada. No se si debería decirlo en un foro abierto, pero estaba impresionada. (Risas) Y podría ser porque era su primera entrevista, pero le hice preguntas, y ¿sabes que? ¡Él las respondió! (Risas) (Aplausos) No hubo giros, no hubo vueltas, no hubo una espera de cinco minutos para volver al punto. No tuve que seguir interrumpiendo, algo por lo que soy conocida, porque quiero que la gente responda a las preguntas. Y él me respondió y fue muy interesante Y dijo-- CH: Cuéntame lo que dijo. CA: No, no, te toca. CH: Tú eres el que interrumpe, yo escucho CA: No,no, te toca. CH: ¿Qué te dijo? CA: Has hablado sobre nacionalismo y tribalismo hoy. Le pregunté, "¿Cómo tuviste el valor de confrontar las tendencias dominantes de la antiglobalización, nacionalismo, populismo cuando ves lo que ha pasado con Brexit, cuando ves lo que pasó en EE. UU. y lo que pudo haber pasado en muchas elecciones europeas al comienzo de 2017?" Y él dijo, "Para mí el nacionalismo significa guerra. Lo hemos visto antes, lo hemos vivido en carne propia en mi continente y soy muy claro al respecto". Así que él no iba solo por lo políticamente conveniente, asumió el mínimo común denominador asumido en otras elecciones políticas. Y él se enfrentó a Marine Le Pen, quien es una mujer muy peligrosa. CH: Última pregunta,Christiane. Cuéntenos ideas dignas de difundir ¿Si pudieses plantar una idea en las mentes de todos aquí cual sería? CA: Yo diría ten cuidado de donde obtienes la información, asume responsabilidad por lo que lees, escuchas y miras. Asegúrate de ir a los grupos fiables para obtener información, no importa si tienes una amplio consumo ecléctico, quédate con las marcas que conoces, porque en este mundo ahora en este instante nuestras crisis, nuestros desafíos, nuestros problemas son tan severos que al menos que estemos todos conectados como ciudadanos globales que aprecian la verdad, que entienden la evidencia científica o empírica y los hechos, estaremos divagando hacia una potencial catástrofe. Así que diría la verdad y luego volvería a Emmanuel Macron y hablaría sobre amor. Yo diría que no hay suficiente amor. Y le pregunté que me hablara sobre amor. Le dije, "Su matrimonio es el tópico de una obsesión global" (Risas) "¿Puedes hablarme de amor? ¿Qué significa para Ud.?" Nunca le pregunté a un presidente o líder elegido sobre el amor Pensé que tendría que intentarlo. y él dijo, realmente me respondió. Y él dijo, "Amo a mi esposa ella es parte de mí, estamos juntos hace décadas" Pero esto es lo que me contó que realmente me quedé. Él dijó, "Es muy importante para mí tener alguien en casa que me diga la verdad". Así que lo traje a mi hogar hablemos sobre la verdad. (Risas) CH: Así que ahí lo tienes. Verdad y amor. Ideas dignas de difundir. Christiane Amanpour, muchas gracias. Fue un gusto. (Aplausos) CA: Gracias CH: Fue un placer. CA: Gracias.